In the previous lecture, we learnt about foundation model evaluation on better and then we
looked at the guard rails in Amazon better. Now in this lecture, we are going to focus on
Amazon SageMaker clarify which focuses on bias detection and explainability.
Okay, now let's try and understand this in more detail. Okay, before we get into how
SageMaker clarified detects bias and explainability. Let's see the phases where potential bias
could creep in. Now let's say we have a model and this is trained on the training data.
Now the training data itself has bias data and then the outcome that is going to be generated
by the model is going to be biased. Then the second one is if the model itself is biased,
then the outcome it's going to generate will be biased. Now let's see in the real life cycle
where SageMaker clarify has a role to play. So the first one is the pre-training data bias as we
just discussed and here the SageMaker clarify can detect and major bias in the raw data before it is
used to train a model. Now the second phase where there could be biases post-training data bias
and model bias. So clarify can detect and major bias emanating from data or model and this is
during the phase when the model has already been deployed. And then we have the third phase where
the model has already been deployed and clarify can help with model explainability. So what does
that mean? So what it can do is it can predict why a model generated a negative outcome.
Now let's say the Java model is to approve or reject a credit card application. So if it
rejects a credit card application that is called as a negative outcome. So clarify can help explain
why the model predicted a negative outcome. It can also explain how the model makes a prediction.
And then finally it can also define which features have the largest influence on the behavior of
the model. Now let's try and understand this through an example. Now this is a data I have taken
from AWS. Here the objective of the model is to predict whether the individual income is more than
$50,000 or less than $50,000 per year. Now what we're going to do is we're going to feed all these
data points to a model such as age, work, class, education, marriage status, occupation,
relationship, ethnic group, gender, hours per week that it works, the country it works in,
and then based on all these data points the model can predict whether the income of the individual
be less than $50,000 or more than $50,000. So now these are all the features we have in our data.
And let's assume that we want to determine whether there is any bias based on the gender.
So here we have the gender and male and female. Now the dataset that AWS had is much
larger but I have just included five records here. And if I take a look at the five records you can
see the out of the five the four records have gender as male and only one record has gender as female.
Now if this is the training data that we use to train the model you can imagine how the accuracy
of the model would be when it is trying to determine for the gender female if the income is less
than or more than $50,000. Because the number of records for female are so low it is very unlikely
that model prediction would be as good as it is for males. So now this is an output generated
based on the larger dataset that AWS has. And in the training dataset you can see the number
of records are heavily biased 67.6% for men and 32.4% for women. So if I calculate the CI or class
imbalance so it's this minus this which is 0.352. This is how you can define which features you want
to review for bias in the raw data. Now let's take a look. Now let's look at the second aspect
on model bias okay. So we'll take the same dataset and you can see and you can see here on
the left you have the positive outcomes as 13.7% and negative outcomes as 86.3. Now the positive
outcome is if it predicted the individual income is more than $50,000 and it predicted 13.7 could have
more than $50,000 and negative is if it is less than $50,000. Now let's take a look at the same
for women. So you can see the positive outcome is only for 4.5% and negative is for 95.5%.
So you can use a matrix called as DPPL which is also called as difference in positive proportion
in labels. Difference you can see here is if you have this as 0.137 and this is 4.5. So 0.045
and this is the value in bias we get. Now let's look at the third aspect which is model
explainability using clarifying. So you can see here clarify helps explain the model
prediction. So it can identify which are the features that contribute most to the model prediction.
So let's say it could be maybe country, occupation, work class. So it will define which are those
factors that contribute most to the model prediction. And it can also help you determine if a particular
model input has more influence than expected on the overall model behavior. So here is a screenshot
from clarifying you can see and it identifies which are the features that are contributing
most towards the model prediction. And this can go a great way in removing the perception
that AI models are black boxes. We'll look at Amazon clarifying. Now let's go and look at
Amazon SageMaker model monitor which focuses on controllability, data and model performance.
And this works in the phase of deploy and monitor after the AI system has been deployed in
production. Now SageMaker focused on bias and explainability. And this focuses on data quality
or the input data that that goes to the model in the production environment. Then it also looks at
model quality while it's deployed in production. Now let's take a look at the same example
that we looked at previously. So we are basically providing this as an input to the model and then
it predicts whether the income is more or less than $50,000. Now let's say this is the dataset that
we had used for the model while training. Now let's say in production lot of the values related to
the occupation are coming as null value. So we are not getting any details on these. Similarly maybe
the details related to the country we're getting lot of null values. Now let's say these two
factors had maximum influence on predicting the individual income. But if you're getting a lot of
these as null values then the quality of data that goes as an input to the model is poor and
this the prediction would not be that great. So this is what the Amazon SageMaker model
monitor focuses on data quality. So it monitors the statistical properties against the ground-to-data
which could be our training data and it evaluates if there are any missing columns, null values
compared to what the model was trained on. The second thing it focuses on is model performance.
So you can define the parameters where you want to evaluate the model performance such as accuracy
precision in the production environment. And we had already earlier discussed about the model
evaluation while using the Amazon bedrock model evaluator. SageMaker also provides a service
where it allows you to evaluate the model performance based on the metrics that you set. Okay,
that's pretty much it from this lecture. I hope you like this lecture. I'll see you in the next
lecture.